Hi folks and welcome to our first tutorial. In this tutorial we will focus on the installation
of ALMA, Linux Operating System, in which later we will install database, we will treat
it as a web server, MySQL server and also we will install Docker and implement Terraform
and other DevOps tools on it. So the first thing here to consider is specification
for the virtual machine. Here for example if you can see you have another machine which
is called asterisk. This asterisk is an APBX system, it is required or recommended to
have four gigabits of memory, two processor and 60 hard disk SSD hard disk speeds. So
here we will install, we need to specify first a new virtual machine and this time we need
to select, okay is isofile, we have already downloaded isofile of ALMA Linux, this ALMA Linux
we will install Docker on it, we will implement some labs later related to Docker MySQL
and we use other dev ops on it, so we need first to select it, okay and of course the VM
where couldn't detect which operating system in this disk image, so this Linux system
is very similar to actually the Linux Red Hat, okay where is the Linux Red Hat, it is Red Hat
Enterprise version 9, it is very similar to it, it is actually the successor of it, so
we will select it first, okay and let me let's rename the virtual machines, for example
here Linux ALMA, okay and let's select storage, we have external storage, so we need to put
it on here and make it for example, make a new folder and we call it ALMA Linux, okay
by the way it is version that it can later after the decommissioning of the centers operating
system, so we use it, okay this is storage, okay and click on next and here we will set
the recommendation for the hard disk sites as following, we will store it as a single
file and we will set it to 100 gigabytes, okay and let's hear customized hardware, we will
set it actually to the recommended specification which means here the memory, we will make
it a moderate one, not too high, not too low, so we set it to this size for example, okay,
so it is about eight gigabytes, we will still use two processor core, okay we have two processor,
number of cores, we will use two, okay and number of cores for processor it is one and
here we will use bridge, okay so this bridge will be used as a connection, so that our
bridge and machines will be bridged to our Wi-Fi network here, okay and we selected already
the hard disk space, so we set all the recommended specifications, okay so we will now close
it, okay and let's now power this virtual machine to start installation for the ALMA links,
okay we install ALMA links, actually we have this is the latest version 9.7, okay,
9.6 is not working no more so we install 9.7, okay so now we will start the graphical
user interface installation, we will select installation language to be English, okay, continue
okay this is the default setting, okay automatic partitioning is detected, okay this is a language
support keyboard, okay so we need here to make two action the root password so let's first
make the root password
okay here we have set the root password, so let's create standard user for example my name
I'm not no more, let's type full name, okay so user name here is M no more for example and
let's set the password for zoos, let's now partition the system, okay we install the
operating system on this hard disk flung, you give it, okay now we have
set our system to be installed, we have set already the hard disk now the root password
user password, okay and now we are ready to go, let's begin installation, okay now we
have finished the installation, so let's reboot the system now, let's resume the video
the installation took about maximum of 20 minutes and after that when you restart it the
system should be working, okay now we have installed the system let's log in with the
user number number, okay as as you can see now the system is installed with the
genome or installed using the desktop version actually I have installed the
desktop version so that I can not just use terminals or run comments but I can use
also graphical user interface tool, so for example here if I want to change the
wired connectivity, okay let's go to wired connection, wired settings, okay and here I
want just to set IP addresses, it is set automatic, with the range this is our
Wi-Fi range 122 and 168 100 and it took from the DHCP the default address of
14 and this is our DNS server and this is our default route, so here for
example if I say I want to check what is internal network or for our Wi-Fi let's
use IP address to make sure here from the details we can see it is from the
same range, so let's now make the IP address static, okay let's go to IP version
4 we not set it to be automatic no more, let's set it to be manual here 192.68.100, let's set it to 20
for example let's set let's now set the subnet mask 255 255 255 0, okay and let's set
the gateway to connect to the internet, okay and for the DNS we will not take the
same address here for the router, as you can see here it took the IP address of the
router which is 192.168.101 we'll set it to be the DNS to be 888 which is a Google DNS
server IP address, so let's set it to manual, let's set it to manual and put it here 888, okay and
let's apply it, okay to be applied we need to just disable the connection and
enable it, and if you can see here you can see that it took IP address, this is our static
IP address, okay and this is our global DNS, this is the default route here, okay so now
we have finished the first step, okay with the installation we have installed our
malinics, we have configured static IP addresses in the upcoming session of section 1, we
will configure which we know how to change host name and make some basic configuration
for the firewall and we installed some system updates and installed the docker but this time
we will use not the graphic user interface, now we will use comment or comment line,
so stay tuned, thank you.